Navigation is an excellent example of a computationally hard problem
导航作为一个很棘手的计算难题
that AI can help solve more efficiently.
很好地体现了人工智能的作用 有了人工智能 问题就能更高效地得到解决
&gt;&gt; What do you mean by computationally hard,
你说很棘手的计算难题是什么意思？
problems that have a high time or space complexity?
是指那些具有高时间或空间复杂度的问题吗？
&gt;&gt; Yeah, precisely.
对的 就是这些
Let me illustrate.
我来具体说明一下吧
I'm trying to plan a road trip from Manchester to Sheffield in the UK and
我打算制定一条公路旅行路线 从英国曼彻斯特到谢菲尔德市
for that, I wish to find the shortest path between them.
而且我想找出最短路线
Given the information about where different cities and
知道了不同城市和市镇
towns are located and
的位置
what roadways connect them, can I use a computer to do the hard work for me?
以及连接这些城镇的道路 我能不能让计算机帮我解决这个难题呢？
&gt;&gt; Sure, this seem like a simple search problem to do graph of city nodes
— 当然可以 这听起来就像个简单的搜索问题 我们只需绘制城市节点
connected by road edges.
以及连接节点的公路边缘
Breadth-first search can handle that, right?
用宽度优先搜索就能解决 对吧？
&gt;&gt; Yeah, but look what happens when I apply breadth-first search.
是的 但看看我用宽度优先搜索之后的结果
It starts considering all the possible paths out of the source city til
搜索会考虑从起始城市出发的所有可能路线
it reaches the desired destination on one of those paths.
直到在这些路线中找出能抵达目的城市的那条
&gt;&gt; That's not very efficient and you're only showing major roadways.
那可不怎么高效啊 而且你这显示的只有主要道路
If you consider smaller streets and alleys,
可如果把小街道、小巷也考虑进去
I'm guessing the space of possible paths to search can easily become intractable.
我想搜索可能路线所需的空间很快就要大得失控了
&gt;&gt; Right, and that's where AI comes in.
对的 所以这个时候就要用到人工智能了
Tell me, if you were manually planning this trip,
告诉我 如果手动规划这次旅行
how would you approach the problem?
你会怎么解决这个问题？
&gt;&gt; Well, I can see that Sheffield is in the east and
恩 我看到谢菲尔德是在曼彻斯特的东边 偏南方
slightly south of Manchester, so I'd probably only consider the few major
所以我可能会只考虑几条主要车道
roadways that are coming out in that direction.
就通向那个方向的那些
Paths that I see going too far away from my destination,
至于看起来就离目的地太远的道路
I might just ignore them or keep them aside to be considered later.
我可能就直接忽略了 或者先放到一边 晚点再考虑
I would definitely give priority to paths that I can see are getting me
我肯定是先考虑那些看起来
closer to my destination.
能带我接近目的地的路线
&gt;&gt; There you go, that's a perfectly fine heuristic to use.
就是这样 这是个极好的启发法
&gt;&gt; I don't know how to drive stick actually.
说实话 我不知道齐发法是什么
&gt;&gt; Heuristic.
是启发法
&gt;&gt; That's AI for smarts.
那是人工智能的智慧所在
Basically, a heuristic is some additional piece of information, a rule,
基本上 启发法指的是一些额外的信息 比如一条规则、
function or constraint, that informs an otherwise brute-force algorithm
一个函数或一个限制 告知暴力算法
to act in a more optimal manner.
以更优化的方式来计算
&gt;&gt; I see, but what I just described seems too imprecise to be
我知道了 但我刚才说的好像不够准确
factored into a real algorithm.
不能作为真正的算法使用啊
&gt;&gt; You will be surprised.
你会大开眼界的
Let's draw a straight line between the source and destination.
我们先在起始地和目的地之间画一条直线
This is the shortest possible path we could ever take
这就是我们能找到的最短可能路线了
if the two cities were directly connected.
如果两座城市是直接相通的话
&gt;&gt; Right, as the crow flies.
对的 乌鸦就会这么飞过去
&gt;&gt; Yeah, now let's consider taking a random step in any direction.
是的 现在我们来想想 随机向任意方向走一步
The new direct distance to the destination has changed.
那么前往目的地的直接距离就有了变化
In fact, it has become greater,
事实上 变得更大了
which means we have effectively gone away from the destination.
也就意味着 我们有效地偏离了目的地
Let's consider a different step.
我们走另一步看看
&gt;&gt; This time it looks like our distance has shrunk so
看起来这次距离缩小了
we have moved closer to our goal.
我们离目标更近了
&gt;&gt; That's right,
对的
we keep testing all possible next steps from the current position and
从现有位置出发 我们不断测试所有可能的下一步
pick the one with the smallest direct distance to move to next.
然后选一步离下一步的直线距离最小的
&gt;&gt; Hm, one thing you haven't considered though is that it seems like
唔 可你没有考虑到一点 虽然现在的下一步
the current next step that seems like the best choice
看起来像是最佳选择
may not turn out to be on the optimal path.
但最后可能不在最佳路线上
&gt;&gt; Good catch.
说得好
Note that we are only using our direct distance heuristic to decide which step
注意 我们只用直接距离启发法来决定
to explore next.
下一步要探索哪里
We're not really throwing away the other possibilities, merely storing them for
我们并不是真的把其它可能性都抛开了 只是把它们储存起来
later consideration, in case none of the more promising paths works out.
以备考虑 免得那些看起来更好的路线都没有用
&gt;&gt; Okay, so this helps us prioritize how our algorithm considers and
好 所以这是在帮我们指引算法去优先考虑
evaluates different possibilities.
和评估某些可能性
I can see that it may prevent some unnecessary searching,
这倒或许能避免一些不必要的搜索
but how effective is it really?
但能多有效呢？
&gt;&gt; Well, let's run it and figure out.
我们来运行看看
&gt;&gt; Neat.
好
It does seem to explore some additional paths, but
看着的确探索了些额外的路线
it converges on the optimal direction pretty quickly.
但很快就汇聚到最优方向上了
&gt;&gt; Yeah, the exact method here is called A* Search and
是的 这个算法叫 A* 搜索
is one of the most popular, yet effective, AI algorithms out there.
是目前最流行 也是最有效的人工智能算法之一
We'll learn more about it in the search lesson.
在搜索课程中 我们会更深入地学习该算法